A Guide to the Margaret S. Marston Lampe Papers 1978-87
Digital Libraries and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Libraries and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Margaret S. Marston Lampe Papers 1978-87
Digital Libraries and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms91-003
5 cubic feet, 5 boxes, 115 folders.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Margaret S. Marston Lampe was born in Arizona in 1941, but has been a long-time resident of Arlington, Virginia. While active in numerous civic and community organizations, she has been most involved with educational issues on the state and national level. Her activities in the area of education have included: chair of the Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers; chair of the National Institute of Education Task Force on Educational Laboratories; and co-chair of the Governmental Affairs Committee of the National Association of State Boards of Education.
Ms. Lampe was selected as a member of the National Commission on Excellence in Education when it was established on August 6, 1981, by U.S. Secretary of Education Terrel H. Bell. The purpose of the Commission was to "spearhead a major campaign to encourage all of America's schools, colleges, and universities to enhance excellence in education. The Secretary directed the Commission to "examine the quality of education in the United States and to make a report to the nation and to him within 18 months of its first meeting." The Commission's first meeting was October 9-10, 1981. Its final report, A Nation at Risk: The Imperative for Education Reform, was issued on April 26, 1983. A "Nation at Risk" Third Anniversary Conference was held on April 25-26, 1986.
In 1986, Ms. Lampe was appointed by Virginia Governor Gerald L. Baliles to Governor's Commission on Excellence in Education. The Commission was charged with considering and recommending actions that would "place Virginia's public elementary and secondary schools into the first rank in education in the nation." The Commission had its impetus from recommendations from the 1984 Governor's Commission on Virginia's Future. The Commission issued its final report in October 1986.
From 1979 to 1987, Ms. Lampe served on the Virginia Board of Education. While serving on the board, she was especially concerned with the issues of textbook censorship and sex education in the schools. In 1988, she was named to the Board of Visitors of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Margaret S. Marston Lampe span the dates 1978-1987 and are comprised mostly of correspondence, final report drafts, briefing material, meeting minutes, and newspaper clippings. The collection is organized into the following series: National Commission on Excellence in Education, Elementary and Secondary Mathematics, National Institute of Education Laboratory, Governor's Commission on Excellence in Education, and Virginia Board of Education.
The majority of this collection contains material from the National Commission on Excellence in Education, of which Ms. Lampe was an original member of the 18 person National Committee. Included in this series are commissioned papers and statements heard before the US House of Represenatives with the intention to raise the standards of education in the United States from schools to colleges and universities. Also included in this inventory is material from the Virginia Board of Education, which Ms. Lampe served on for eight years. Material includes notes and research on sex education and textbook censorship.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to subject matter.
Description of Series
NATIONAL COMMISSION ON EXCELLENCE IN EDUCATION 1982-83, n.d.
Contains briefing material on educational and regional work sessions. Also includes a statement heard before the before U.S. Senate Committee on Labor and Human Resources.
ELEMENTARY AND SECONDARY MATHEMATICS 1982-83, n.d.
Includes briefing material, notes, site visit for gifted and talented students, and final report drafts.
NATIONAL COMMISSION ON EXCELLENCE IN EDUCATION 1981-83, n.d.
Contains final report designs, subcommittee meetings, hearing on teaching and teacher education, commissioned papers and fact sheets. Also included a published copy of the final report "A Nation at Risk: The Imperative for Educational Reform."
NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF EDUCATION LABORATORY 1976-86, n.d.
Contains Governor's commission on Virginia's future, US department of Education secretary's study group, and the National Business Consortium for the gifted and talented. Also includes the 20th Century Fund Conference on Merit Pay and Master Teacher Program.
GOVERNOR'S COMMISSION ON EXCELLENCE IN EDUCATION 1986-89, n.d.
Includes corespondence, agendas, minutes, resource material, and reports. Also includes the final report of "Excellence in Education: A Plan for Virginia's Future."
VIRGINIA BOARD OF EDUCATION 1983-86, n.d.
Contains correspondence and newspaper clippings on textbook censorship, Republican Women's Leadership Forum, Title 22 revisions, photographs, and miscellaneous newspaper clippings and articles.
Contents List
- National Commission on Excellence in Education 1982-83, n.d.
  - Cooperative Education n.d. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Briefing Material on Parents Role in Education 1982 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Briefing Material for Regional Work Sessions February 16 & 18, 1983 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Statement by David P. Gardner, Commission Chairman, before U.S. Senate Committee on Labor and Human Resources November 9, 1983 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Elementary and Secondary Mathematics 1982-83, n.d.
  - Science, and Technology Education n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Briefing Material on Education of the Gifted and Talented Students n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Site Visit: Education for Gifted and Talented Students October 14, 1982 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Notes: "Equity and Excellence" n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - College Curriculum: Shape, Influence, and Assessment August 27-28, 1982 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Public and Private Schools n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Reading Material n.d. (Box-folder 1-11-18)
  - Recommendations March 25, 1983 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Notes n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Final Report: Facing the Issues of Cooperative Education (Region III Hearing/Conference) October 11, 1982 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Distribution of Final Report n.d. (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Final Report Draft February 25, 1983 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Final Report Draft March 18, 1983 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Final Report Draft April 6, 1983 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Final Report Draft n.d. (Box-folder 1-26)
- National Commission on Excellence in Education 1981-83, n.d.
  - Forum on Recommendations June 30, 1983 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Comments n.d. (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Responses to Final Report n.d. (Box-folder 1-29-31)
  - Final Report Design n.d. (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Meeting October 9, 1981 (Box-folder 2-33)
  - Meetings November 6, 16, & December 7, 1981 (Box-folder 2-34)
  - Meeting December 7, 1981 (Box-folder 2-35)
  - Meeting April 23-24, 1982 (Box-folder 2-36)
  - Meeting April 30, 1982 (Box-folder 2-37)
  - Meeting - Briefing Material May 25, 1982 (Box-folder 2-38)
  - Meeting September 28-29, 1982 (Box-folder 2-39)
  - Meeting November 15-16, 1982 (Box-folder 2-40)
  - Working Papers January 20-22, 1983 (Box-folder 2-41)
  - Working Papers February, 1983 (Box-folder 2-42)
  - Work Session March 2-4, 1983 (Box-folder 2-43)
  - Preliminary Classification of Notable Programs Profile: Post-Secondary n.d. (Box-folder 2-44)
  - Presentation by Stephen Bailey 1981 (Box-folder 2-45)
  - Perspectives on Excellence in Education - Briefing Material February, 1982 (Box-folder 2-46)
  - Hearing on Teaching and Teacher Education May 11-12 (Box-folder 2-47-48)
  - Hearing on Teaching and Teacher Education Staff Summary n.d. (Box-folder 2-49)
  - Hearing on Science, Mathematics, and Technology Education March 11-12, 1982 (Box-folder 2-50)
  - Hearing on Language and Literacy - Briefing Material April 16, 1982 (Box-folder 2-51-52)
  - Commissioned Paper: "Time on Task: A Research Review" by Nancy Karweit October, 1982 (Box-folder 2-53)
  - Commissioned Paper: "Motivational Factors in School Achievement" by Martin Maehr October 26, 1982 (Box-folder 2-54)
  - Subcommittee Meeting March 19, 1983 (Box-folder 2-55)
  - Statement Before the Subcommittee on Elementary, Secondary, and Vocational Education, U.S. House of Representatives May 12, 1983 (Box-folder 2-56)
  - Secondary School Recognition Program n.d. (Box-folder 2-57)
  - "A Nation at Risk" Third Anniversary Conference April 25-26, 1983 (Box-folder 2-58)
  - "A Nation At Risk: The Imperative for Educational Reform" (published copy of final report) n.d. (Box-folder 2-59)
  - Fact Sheet February 1982 (Box-folder 3-60)
  - Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 3-61)
  - U.S. Department of Education Regional Offices n.d. (Box-folder 3-62)
  - Photograph n.d. (Box-folder 3-63)
  - Overhead Presentation n.d. (Box-folder 3-64)
  - National Forum on Excellence in Education 1983 (Box-folder 3-65)
  - National Academy of Sciences Convocation on Pre-College Education in Mathematics and Sciences 1982 (Box-folder 3-66)
  - Project Equality n.d. (Box-folder 3-67)
- National Institute of Education Laboratory 1976-86, n.d.
  - Study Group n.d. (Box-folder 3-68)
  - 20th Century Fund Conference on Merit Pay and Master Teacher Program November 4, 1983 (Box-folder 3-69)
  - Perspective Principal Assessment Centers May 21, 1986 (Box-folder 3-70)
  - Distinguished School Board Panel n.d. (Box-folder 3-71)
  - National Business Consortium for the Gifted and Talented n.d. (Box-folder 3-72)
  - National Association of State Boards of Education n.d. (Box-folder 3-73)
  - U.S. Department of Education Secretary's Study Group on the Quality of Textbooks and Instructional Materials 1984 (Box-folder 3-74)
  - Virginia Plan for Equal Opportunity in State-Supported Institutions of Higher Education 1983 (Box-folder 3-75)
  - Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers 1976-79 (Box-folder 3-76)
  - Virginia Statewide Conference on Textbooks Reform May 8-9, 1986 (Box-folder 3-77)
  - Governor's Commission on Virginia's Future 1982-83 (Box-folder 3-78)
- Governor's Commission on Excellence in Education 1986, 1989, n.d.
  - Plan of Action n.d. (Box-folder 3-79)
  - Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 3-80)
  - "Report Card" October 1989 (Box-folder 3-81)
  - Agendas, Minutes, and Supporting Documents n.d. (Box-folder 3-82)
  - Minutes April 28, 1986 (Box-folder 3-83)
  - Resource Materials n.d. (Box-folder 3-84-85)
  - Reading Material n.d. (Box-folder 3-86)
  - Newspaper Clippings n.d. (Box-folder 3-87)
  - "Excellence in Education: A Plan for Virginia's Future" (Final Report) October 1986 (Box-folder 3-88)
  - Commission on Arlington's (Virginia) Future n.d. (Box-folder 3-89)
  - Reports n.d. (Box-folder 3-90)
  - Education Taskforce n.d. (Box-folder 3-91)
- Virginia Board of Education 1983, 1986, n.d.
  - Organization and Functions (Briefing Paper Presented to Governor Baliles) 1986 (Box-folder 4-92)
  - Textbook Censorship n.d. (Box-folder 4-93-100)
  - Textbook Censorship - Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 4-101)
  - Textbook Censorship - Newspaper Clippings n.d. (Box-folder 4-102)
  - Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 4-103)
  - Title 22 Revisions n.d. (Box-folder 4-104)
  - Sex Education n.d. (Box-folder 4-105)
  - Newspaper Clippings n.d. (Box-folder 4-106)
  - Correspondence - General n.d. (Box-folder 4-107-108)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Education n.d. (Box-folder 4-109)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Margaret Lampe n.d. (Box-folder 4-110-113)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Margaret Sanger n.d. (Box-folder 4-114)
  - Photographs n.d. (Box-folder 4-115)
  - Video Tape: Goldberg/Marston, Fairfax High School May 11, 1983
  - Republican Women's Leadership Forum (notebook) n.d.
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings and Articles n.d.
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings and Articles n.d. (Box 5)